<?xml version='1.0'?>
<content>
<title>about xml-qstat</title>
<heading>About xml-qstat</heading>




<!-- section -->
<section>
<sectionHead>What is xml-qstat?</sectionHead>
<para><![CDATA[
xml-qstat is an attempt to do something useful with the XML status information
that GridEngine 6 <a href="http://gridengine.sunsource.net">(http://gridengine.sunsource.net</a>
&amp; <a href="http://sun.com/software/gridware/">http://www.sun.com/software/gridware/</a>)
is now able to produce. In previous attempts to build web based GridEngine
monitoring tools, the text based Grid status and monitoring tools were
crudely parsed and wrapped into simple web CGI's:
<div>
<a href="../images/screenshot/xmlqstat_011.png"><img border="0" alt="*" src="../images/screenshot/xmlqstat_011_thumb.png"/></a>
Yielded ...
<a href="../images/screenshot/xmlqstat_013.png"><img border="0" alt="*" src="../images/screenshot/xmlqstat_013_thumb.png"/></a>
</div>
]]></para>

<para>
At its heart, xml-qstat consists of a collection of stylesheets written in
XSL. The stylesheets can be used with a XSLT transformation engine to change
raw GridEngine XML data into convenient formats such as XHTML and RSS. Once
the grid data has been mapulated into XHTML we can then apply other web
technologies such as CSS, DHTML and Javascrip to create fairly sophisticated
web based tools for GridEngine status reporting and monitoring.
</para>
<para><![CDATA[
The current version of this software has been developed to run under the
<a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/2.1/">Apache Cocoon (2.1)</a> XML
publishing framework.
]]></para>
</section>


<!-- section -->
<section>
<sectionHead>History</sectionHead>

<para><![CDATA[
This is a 3rd generation codebase of a project that was begun in mid-2005.
Early versions of this program used Xalan-C++
(<a href="http://xml.apache.org/xalan-c/">http://xml.apache.org/xalan-c/</a>)
but that package turned out to be difficult to build on various Linux and
Apple OS X systems.  The 2nd generation xml-qstat programs and CGIs used the
very nice Perl modules
<strong>XML::LibXML</strong> and <strong>XML::LibXSLT</strong>.
Those modules provided Perl intefaces to the Gnome Project's excellent
<strong>libxml2</strong> (<a href="http://www.xmlsoft.org">http://www.xmlsoft.org</a>/)
and <strong>libxslt</strong>
(<a href="http://xmlsoft.org/XSLT/">http://xmlsoft.org/XSLT/</a>)
code libraries. The 2nd generation code was abandoned when
<a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/2.1/">Apache Cocoon</a> was discovered
- the Cocoon framework functions out of the box on just about any Java
enabled system and there are no requirements to download and build various
dependent XML libraries and Perl modules.

<br/><br/>
This is what generation 2 (pure Perl) looked like:
<div><a href="../images/screenshot/Mozillaxml_qstat_001.jpg"><img border="0" alt="*" src="../images/screenshot/Mozillaxml_qstat_001.thumb.jpg"/></a>
<a href="../images/screenshot/Mozillaxml_qstat_002.jpg"><img border="0" alt="*" src="../images/screenshot/Mozillaxml_qstat_002.thumb.jpg"/></a>
</div>
]]></para>
</section>


<!-- section -->


<!-- section -->
<section>
<sectionHead>Discussion List</sectionHead>
<para><![CDATA[
A mailing list has been set up for xml-qstat discussion. More information about
the list including instructions on how to join or access the list archives can
be found online at
<a href="http://bioteam.net/mailman/listinfo/xml-qstat-d">http://bioteam.net/mailman/listinfo/xml-qstat-d</a>
]]></para>
</section>


<!-- section -->
<section>
<sectionHead>Resources</sectionHead>
<para><![CDATA[
It turns out that getting at GridEngine XML and pulling out the data one is
interested in is actually pretty easy. The hardest part of this project is
actually the web design and interface aspects. The following references were
invaluable during the course of initial experiments and the eventual code:
<ul>
  <li><b>&quot;Learning XSLT&quot; by Michael Fitzgerald, 2nd ed. (2004), O'Reilly</b></li>
  <li>&quot;Javascript &amp; DHTML Cookbook&quot; by Danny Goodman, 1st ed (2003), O'Reilly</li>
  <li>&quot;Javascript Bible&quot; by Danny Goodman with Michael Morrison, 5th ed. (2003), Wiley</li>
  <li>&quot;Web Designers Reference: An integrated approach to web design with XHTML and CSS&quot; by Craig Grannel, 2005, friendsof</li>

  <li>&quot;Eric Meyer on CSS: Mastering the language of web design&quot; by Eric Meyer, 2003, New Riders Publishing</li>
  <li>&quot;More Eric Meyer on CSS&quot;, by Eric Meyer, 2004, New Riders Publishing</li>
</ul>
<br/>

]]></para>
</section>

<!-- section -->
<section>
<sectionHead>Customization and Development Links</sectionHead>
<para><![CDATA[
Additional information for people insterested in customizing this package:
<ul>
  <li><a href="../info/links.html">Additional Links</b></li>

</ul>
<br/><br/>

]]></para>
</section>


</content>

